<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-27T17:31:45-04:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">5e Spell Reviews</title><subtitle>In-depth reviews of spells for 5th edition Dungeons &amp; Dragons.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Phantom Steed</title><link href="/2018/06/21/phantom-steed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phantom Steed" /><published>2018-06-21T16:18:13-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-21T16:18:13-04:00</updated><id>/2018/06/21/phantom-steed</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/06/21/phantom-steed.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/phantom-steed&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phantom Steed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a 3rd-level illusion spell for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/wizard&quot;&gt;Wizard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/fighter#EldritchKnight&quot;&gt;Eldritch Knight&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/rogue#ArcaneTrickster&quot;&gt;Arcane Trickster&lt;/a&gt;. Wizards gets 3rd-level spells when they reach 5th level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arcane Trickster and Eldritch Knight get 3rd-level spells when they reach 13th level. By that time, other classes are casting 7th-level spells like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/plane-shift&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plane Shift&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/teleport&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teleport&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;Phantom Steed&lt;/em&gt; is one of the 3rd-level spells that are still useful at high levels of play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-it-do&quot;&gt;What does it do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spell allows you to summon a spirit horse with a speed of 100, which is faster than nearly any other mount in the game. It can be cast as a ritual, requires no material components, and lasts for 1 hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-uses&quot;&gt;Possible uses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cast this spell in advance of a battle to give yourself or the front-line combatants in your party improved mobility on the battlefield. On a Phantom Steed, the Barbarian is as mobile as the Monk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put the Rogue on a Phantom Steed, and watch them keep 50 feet away from the enemy, riding in for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/compendium/rules/basic-rules/classes#SneakAttack&quot;&gt;Sneak Attack&lt;/a&gt;, then riding back out without provoking &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/compendium/rules/basic-rules/combat#OpportunityAttacks&quot;&gt;attacks of opportunity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cast Phantom Steed every hour on the hour to give yourself an inexhaustible mount that can travel upwards of 90 miles in a single 8-hour day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no limit on the number of Phantom Steeds you can have at any one time, other than that the casting time of the ritual is 11 minutes. So you could summon five of them in 55 minutes and give the whole party spirit horses for 5 minutes. That’s 50 rounds of combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on whether your DM will allow you to cast a spell as a ritual while riding a Phantom Steed (there is nothing in the rules against it), you can use this spell as a reliable way to move the whole party at a speed of 100 miles per day. Cast Phantom Steed 4 times to give 4 members of the party spirit horses for 16 minutes. Then while you’re traveling on those horses at 13 miles per hour, start casting it again. Cast the spell continuously for 8 hours to generate a fresh steed every 11 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compared-with-other-spells&quot;&gt;Compared with other spells&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An obvious comparison is with the spells &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/find-steed&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Find Steed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a 2nd-level Paladin spell) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/find-greater-steed&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Find Greater Steed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a 4th-level Paladin spell). A Phantom Steed is faster than any creature that can be summoned with either of those spells, and &lt;em&gt;does not require a spell slot when cast as a ritual&lt;/em&gt;. Whereas the steeds summoned by the paladin are permanent, the Phantom Steed can be summoned again and again at only the cost of a few minutes of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other 3rd-level spells that improve battlefield mobility are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/fly&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/haste&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Haste&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, both of which require concentration and a spell slot. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/water-walk&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Water Walk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is another 3rd-level spell that improves mobility by allowing you to walk on water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Phantom Steed is a creature, those other spells can be cast on it. What’s better than a spirit horse? A hasted spirit horse that can walk on water. A Phantom Steed with &lt;em&gt;Water Walk&lt;/em&gt; cast on it is three times faster than the fastest ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phantom Steed&lt;/em&gt; is an incredibly versatile utility spell that can drastically improve your mobility on and off the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Phantom Steed is a 3rd-level illusion spell for the Wizard, Eldritch Knight, and Arcane Trickster. Wizards gets 3rd-level spells when they reach 5th level.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Find the Path</title><link href="/2018/06/21/find-the-path.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Find the Path" /><published>2018-06-21T14:49:25-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-21T14:49:25-04:00</updated><id>/2018/06/21/find-the-path</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/06/21/find-the-path.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/find-the-path&quot;&gt;Find the Path&lt;/a&gt; is a 6th level divination spell for the Bard, Cleric, and Druid. It requires your concentration, and as long as your character is concentrating on it (for up to 24 hours), it basically compels the DM to tell you the shortest route to wherever you’re going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spell has a long and venerable history in D&amp;amp;D. In AD&amp;amp;D 2nd edition, &lt;em&gt;Find the Path&lt;/em&gt; let you describe a location in general terms, and the DM would reveal what actions were required to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spell has been significantly reduced in scope in 5th edition. It now requires naming a specific location that is already known to the caster, and an object from the location as a material component. This makes it highly situational. It will be exceedingly useful in cases when:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You’re lost or don’t know the way to where you’re going.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You’re &lt;em&gt;familiar&lt;/em&gt; with the destination. This means you’ve been there before or have seen it with a &lt;em&gt;Scrying&lt;/em&gt; spell or similar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have an object from that place in your possession.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You’re at level 11 or 12, so you don’t have access to 7th-level spells that would let you teleport to the destination (or you’re at a lower level still, and you have a Find the Path scroll).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have time to take a long rest so you can prepare &lt;em&gt;Find the Path&lt;/em&gt;, because let’s face it, you’re not going to have this spell prepared in advance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You’re a Cleric or Druid, because let’s face it, a Bard is never going to pick this spell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transport via Plants is not an option because there are no plants at the destination.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There may be things along the way that you don’t want to skip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall power level of &lt;em&gt;Find the Path&lt;/em&gt; is comparable to other 6th-level spells like Contingency, Druid Grove, Heroes’ Feast, Transport via Plants, and Wind Walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Find the Path&lt;/em&gt; is highly situational, but under specific circumstances it can be very useful. Since it’s a Cleric and Druid spell, it’s always available for when you need it, but for the Bard it’s mostly useless.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Find the Path is a 6th level divination spell for the Bard, Cleric, and Druid. It requires your concentration, and as long as your character is concentrating on it (for up to 24 hours), it basically compels the DM to tell you the shortest route to wherever you’re going.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Misty Step</title><link href="/2018/06/18/misty-step.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Misty Step" /><published>2018-06-18T00:59:15-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-18T00:59:15-04:00</updated><id>/2018/06/18/misty-step</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/06/18/misty-step.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/misty-step&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Misty Step&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a 2nd level conjuration spell from the Player’s Handbook. It’s available to Sorcerers, Warlocks, and Wizards, as well as Druids who choose the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/druid#CircleoftheLand&quot;&gt;Circle of the Land&lt;/a&gt; (coast), and Paladins who choose either the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/paladin#OathoftheAncients&quot;&gt;Oath of the Ancients&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/paladin#OathofVengeance&quot;&gt;Oath of Vengeance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-misty-step-do&quot;&gt;What does Misty Step do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spell is quite straightforward. It allows you to use a bonus action to teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space that you can see. It requires only a verbal component, so it works as long as you can see and speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;potential-uses&quot;&gt;Potential Uses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misty step can improve your mobility on the battlefield. If you have a 2nd level spell slot to spare, you can move to engage with the enemy, make a melee attack with either a weapon or a cantrip, and then Misty Step to safety using your bonus action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make a fast getaway you can use your movement, take the Dash action, and cast Misty Step as a bonus action. If your speed is 30, that lets you travel 90 feet in a single turn. And you can Misty Step onto rooftops or across a chasm where the enemy can’t reach you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also Misty Step into places that you can see but not otherwise get to. If your way is blocked by a barrier that you can see through (like a gate), you can simply Misty Step to the other side of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compared-with-other-spells&quot;&gt;Compared with other spells&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/dimension-door&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dimension Door&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a 4th level spell that allows a similar kind of teleportation, except it takes your action, has a range of 500 feet, and is not limited to target locations that you can see. It also allows you to bring one creature with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misty Step is comparable in power to other 2nd level spells. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/suggestion&quot;&gt;Suggestion&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/invisibility&quot;&gt;Invisibility&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/spider-climb&quot;&gt;Spider Climb&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/levitate&quot;&gt;Levitate&lt;/a&gt; are all 2nd level spells and Misty Step fits well with those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Misty Step&lt;/em&gt; is a solid spell to improve your mobility on the battlefield, get into unreachable places, or give yourself a quick way to retreat. Even as you advance to higher levels, Misty Step continues to make good use of your bonus action and your 2nd level spell slots.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Misty Step is a 2nd level conjuration spell from the Player’s Handbook. It’s available to Sorcerers, Warlocks, and Wizards, as well as Druids who choose the Circle of the Land (coast), and Paladins who choose either the Oath of the Ancients or the Oath of Vengeance.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fire Shield</title><link href="/2018/06/18/fire-shield.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fire Shield" /><published>2018-06-18T00:30:05-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-18T00:30:05-04:00</updated><id>/2018/06/18/fire-shield</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/06/18/fire-shield.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/fire-shield&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fire Shield&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a 4th level evocation spell for Wizards. It’s also available to Warlocks with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/warlock#PactOfTheFiend&quot;&gt;Pact of the Fiend&lt;/a&gt;. It takes an action to cast, and lets you choose to gain resistance to either fire or cold damage. Resistance means damage of the type you choose is halved against you. In addition, while this spell is active, it deals 2d8 damage to any attackers that hit you with a melee attack, and they don’t get a saving throw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spell can be cast only on yourself. The effect lasts for 10 minutes, which is 100 rounds of combat, and does not require concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conveniently, the damage this spell deals is of the opposite kind to the damage that it gives you resistance against. If you choose resistance to fire damage, the spell will deal cold damage to your attackers, and vice versa. Generally, creatures that deal fire damage will be resistant to fire and not cold. Some fire elementals for example are immune to fire damage and vulnerable to cold damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are lots of monsters resistant to both fire and cold damage. Many demons and devils are resistant to cold and immune to fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compared-with-other-spells&quot;&gt;Compared with other spells&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/protection-from-energy&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Protection from Energy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a 3rd level abjuration spell that also grants damage resistance, but does no damage and requires your concentration. &lt;em&gt;Protection from Energy&lt;/em&gt; can be cast on a creature other than yourself, and can grant resistance to acid, lightning, and thunder damage in addition to fire and cold. The duration is longer than &lt;em&gt;Fire Shield&lt;/em&gt; (up to one hour), although the duration can be cut short if you take damage and fail your concentration saving throw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/stoneskin&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stoneskin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is another 4th level spell that grants damage resistance, albeit to far more common types of damage (nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing). Like &lt;em&gt;Protection from Energy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Stoneskin&lt;/em&gt; deals no damage, requires concentration (up to an hour), and lets you cast it on others. &lt;em&gt;Stoneskin&lt;/em&gt; also costs 100 gp each time you cast it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/armor-of-agathys&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Armor of Agathys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a 1st-level abjuration that can be upcast using a 4th-level slot. It does not grant you damage resistance, but for each spell slot level it gives you 5 temporary hit points and deals 5 points of cold damage to attackers that hit you with a melee attack. With a 4th-level slot you get 20 hit points and attackers take 20 points of cold damage. &lt;em&gt;Armor of Agathys&lt;/em&gt; can be a better or worse choice than &lt;em&gt;Fire Shield&lt;/em&gt;, depending on the situation. If you know you’re going to be taking a lot of cold or fire damage, &lt;em&gt;Fire Shield&lt;/em&gt; is clearly better. Otherwise, &lt;em&gt;Armor of Agathys&lt;/em&gt; is probably the better choice, and it’s more flexible as it can be cast using a spell slot of any level. But you don’t have to choose if you don’t want to! You can have &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; of these spells active at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Shield is a solid choice for going into battle with creatures that deal either fire or cold damage, or going into a situation where fire or cold is going to be an obstacle. The fact that it has no Concentration requirement makes this spell really strong. The damage-dealing aspect of it is less useful for glass cannons that stay out of melee range, and there are spells that perform that function better, such as &lt;em&gt;Armor of Agathys&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Fire Shield is a 4th level evocation spell for Wizards. It’s also available to Warlocks with the Pact of the Fiend. It takes an action to cast, and lets you choose to gain resistance to either fire or cold damage. Resistance means damage of the type you choose is halved against you. In addition, while this spell is active, it deals 2d8 damage to any attackers that hit you with a melee attack, and they don’t get a saving throw.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Identify</title><link href="/2018/06/17/identify.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Identify" /><published>2018-06-17T23:23:04-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-17T23:23:04-04:00</updated><id>/2018/06/17/identify</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/06/17/identify.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/identify&quot;&gt;Identify&lt;/a&gt; is a 1st level divination spell from the Basic Rules. The spell is available to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/wizard&quot;&gt;Wizard&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/bard&quot;&gt;Bard&lt;/a&gt;, and automatically given to Clerics of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/cleric#ForgeDomain&quot;&gt;Forge&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/cleric#KlowledgeDomain&quot;&gt;Knowledge&lt;/a&gt; domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-it-do&quot;&gt;What does it do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Identify&lt;/em&gt; lets you immediately learn the properties of a magical item, or know what spells are affecting a creature or object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a minute to cast, and requires a one-time 100 gp investment for the material component, which the spell does not consume. It can be cast as a Ritual, so you can spend an additional ten minutes to cast it without expending a spell slot. If you’re a wizard or bard, you don’t need to have the spell prepared to cast it as a ritual. If you’re a Forge or Knowledge domain cleric, Identify will be a domain spell, so you’ll always have it prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-ways-to-identify-items&quot;&gt;Other ways to identify items&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Dungeon Master’s Guide, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/compendium/rules/dmg/treasure#IdentifyingaMagicItem&quot;&gt;characters can identify a magic item by spending a short rest with it in their possession&lt;/a&gt;. Potions can be identified simply by tasting them. This makes the utility of the &lt;em&gt;Identify&lt;/em&gt; spell a little less obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;em&gt;Identify&lt;/em&gt; works in eleven minutes (or one minute, at the cost of a spell slot) instead of an hour for a short rest. The spell can also identify things you can’t identify by taking a rest. The spell can reveal the properties of basically anything that has been magically created or has a spell affecting it. For example, it can be used to identify a teleportation circle inscribed on the ground. You can also use &lt;em&gt;Identify&lt;/em&gt; to learn which spells are currently affecting a creature or object, if any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Identify&lt;/em&gt; is a thoroughly useful utility spell, especially when cast as a ritual. You could cast &lt;em&gt;Identify&lt;/em&gt; on every object you encounter without expending a single spell slot. At least one person in your party should know this spell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Identify is a 1st level divination spell from the Basic Rules. The spell is available to the Wizard and Bard, and automatically given to Clerics of the Forge and Knowledge domains.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lightning Arrow</title><link href="/2018/06/16/lightning-arrow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lightning Arrow" /><published>2018-06-16T22:39:51-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-16T22:39:51-04:00</updated><id>/2018/06/16/lightning-arrow</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/06/16/lightning-arrow.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/lightning-arrow&quot;&gt;Lightning Arrow&lt;/a&gt; is a 3rd level Ranger spell from the Player’s Handbook. Your Ranger gets two 3rd level spell slots per long rest at 9th level. A that level, a Ranger can know a total of 6 spells, so you need to choose your spells carefully. Should you pick Lightning Arrow over other spells?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-lightning-arrow-do&quot;&gt;What does Lightning Arrow do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightning Arrow takes a bonus action to cast, and changes your next ranged weapon attack to deal lightning splash damage that works whether or not your attack hits. Every creature within 10 feet of the target (including allies) take 2d8 lightning damage, halved on a successful Dexterity saving throw. And instead of taking the normal damage from your weapon, the target of your attack takes 4d8 lightning damage, halved if you miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;statistical-analysis&quot;&gt;Statistical analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s analyze a scenario that might come up in the game. The 9th-level party is faced with eight &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/monsters/dire-wolf&quot;&gt;Dire Wolves&lt;/a&gt;, and it’s the ranger’s turn. She decides to cast Lightning Arrow and attack one of the wolves with her Longbow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/direwolveslarrow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranger casts Lightning Arrow on a Dire Wolf&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say the ranger’s attack bonus is +8. Against the Dire Wolf’s AC of 14, she has a 3 in 4 chance of hitting the wolf with an arrow. She’ll do damage to the wolves in the blue area whether she hits or misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking all that into account, the spell will do an average of 16.5875 points of damage to the targeted dire wolf, and 5.5 to the others. The damage has the following probability distribution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/larrowhistogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Lightning Arrow Damage Histogram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lightning-arrow-compared-with-other-spells&quot;&gt;Lightning Arrow compared with other spells&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other offensive spells available to the Ranger with 3rd level slots include &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/conjure-barrage&quot;&gt;Conjure Barrage&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/wind-wall&quot;&gt;Wind Wall&lt;/a&gt;. Both of those deal 3d8 damage (piercing or bludgeoning, respectively) to creatures in a much larger area, although Lightning Arrow potentially has a much longer range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conjure Barrage is a 60 foot cone, which would allow our ranger to damage all eight of the dire wolves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/direwolvesbarrage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranger casts Conjure Barrage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wind Wall allows you to shape the 50 foot long wall to take pretty much any path you want up to 120 feet away. Here’s how that might look in our situation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/direwolveswindwall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranger casts Wind Wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conjure Barrage and Wind Wall do more damage to more enemies, but Lightning Arrow does twice as much damage on average to a single enemy, which is generally more useful for a Ranger. The Ranger class is really optimized for taking down a single target at a time, so the AoE damage they can do is pretty feeble compared to the arcane casters. If a 9th-level party is going for AoE damage with 3rd-level spell slots, have the Wizards and Sorcerers bust out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/fireball&quot;&gt;Fireballs&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/barragevfireball.png&quot; alt=&quot;Conjure Barrage vs Fireball&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightning Arrow is very similar to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/hail-of-thorns&quot;&gt;Hail of Thorns&lt;/a&gt;, which can be upcast with a 3rd level slot, dealing 3d10 damage to the target and everyone within 5 feet of it. The target also suffers the normal damage from the attack. Since this happens only if your attack hits, the damage output of Hail of Thorns is sometimes zero. Even so, Lightning Arrow does only a couple of points more damage on average (against a Dire Wolf, 16.6 vs 14.3). So all things being equal, Lightning Arrow is a slight upgrade from Hail of Thorns. Compare Hail of Thorns at 3rd level against the Dire Wolves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hailvlarrow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hail of Thorns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fully a quarter of the 3rd level slots used to cast Hail of Thorns in this situation would be completely wasted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/flame-arrows&quot;&gt;Flame Arrows&lt;/a&gt; (from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/compendium/adventures/pota&quot;&gt;Princes of the Apocalypse&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/compendium/rules/xgte&quot;&gt;Xanathar’s Guide to Everything&lt;/a&gt;) is another 3rd level spell for the Ranger that could be compared to Lightning Arrow. Flame Arrows takes an action to cast, adds 1d6 damage to your next twelve attacks, and requires concentration the whole time. Using a single 3rd level slot for Flame Arrows ends up dealing maybe 4 points of damage more per turn on average over 6 turns than using that same slot for Lightning Arrow, but if the Ranger takes damage she might lose her concentration, turning those Flame Arrows into regular arrows again. So Flame Arrows is only better than Lightning Arrow in situations where you’re either fighting enemies vulnerable to fire, you know you’re going to have a drawn-out battle and you’re pretty sure you can shield your Ranger from taking damage, or if you’re up against a lot of enemies and you want to combine Flame Arrows with something like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/characters/classes/ranger#Hunter&quot;&gt;Hunter&lt;/a&gt; archetype’s Volley feature, or a &lt;a href=&quot;https://dndbeyond.com/spells/haste&quot;&gt;Haste&lt;/a&gt; spell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/larrowvfarrow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Lightning Arrow vs Flame Arrows&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enemy-damage-resistance-and-vulnerability&quot;&gt;Enemy damage resistance and vulnerability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 70 different creatures in the official D&amp;amp;D books are resistant to lightning damage, and more than 20 others are totally immune to it. However, many of those creatures have Good alignment, so are unlikely to be enemies in your game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightning Arrow would be ridiculously good against creatures vulnerable to Lightning damage, but no creatures in the official D&amp;amp;D books so far have vulnerability to such damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s rare for creatures to be resistant to the magical piercing and bludgeoning damage of Wind Wall, Conjure Barrage, and Hail of Thorns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;synergy-with-other-ranger-features&quot;&gt;Synergy with other Ranger features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very importantly, Lightning Arrow is an Attack, unlike Conjure Barrage or Wind Wall. Since it’s an Attack, it synergizes nicely with the Archery fighting style, your Extra Attack feature, the Hunter archetype’s animal companion, the Gloom Stalker’s Dread Ambusher and Stalker’s Flurry features, the Horizon Walker’s Planar Warrior and Distant Strike features, as well as the Hunter’s Colossus Slayer, Giant Killer, and Horde Breaker features. Although Lightning Arrow only augments a single attack, these features allow you to make additional attacks either before or after your Lightning Arrow, or add more damage dice to the spell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, the total damage output of a 9th-level Ranger’s turn when casting Lightning Arrow looks more like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/larrowdpr.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranger DPR&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;critical-hits&quot;&gt;Critical Hits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Conjure Barrage, Hail of Thorns, or Wind Wall, Lightning Arrow can benefit from a critical hit. This means that 5% of the time the damage to the target will be 8d8. The splash damage will still be be 2d8. If you average the critical hits over all your uses of Lightning Arrow, it amounts to an additional 2 points of damage per casting. That’s not a lot, but when you do get those critical hits they may turn the tide in any given fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compared-with-other-classes&quot;&gt;Compared with other classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 9th level, the Wizard has access to a 5th level spell slot, letting them cast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dndbeyond.com/spells/cone-of-cold&quot;&gt;Cone of Cold&lt;/a&gt;, a 60-foot cone dealing 8d8 damage. But Lightning Arrow is a 3rd level spell, so let’s compare it with the Wizard’s 3rd level spells. Fireball does 8d6 damage in a 20-foot radius sphere, making Lightning Arrow seem pretty feeble by comparison on its own. That said, you’ll usually be casting Lightning Arrow as part of a combination with multiple attacks on your turn–something that the Wizard cannot do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/larrowdprvfireball.png&quot; alt=&quot;Lightning Arrow DPR vs Fireball&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-you-would-use-this-spell&quot;&gt;When you would use this spell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightning Arrow is a situational combat spell. It’s good for when you want to deal a lot of damage to a single enemy with its allies nearby, or when you might want to prepare an ambush. The saving throw is Dex, which a lot of creatures that fight in close formation might be fairly good at. Since this spell’s splash damage doesn’t discriminate between friend and foe, it’s less useful if your allies are already engaging the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightning Arrow is a strong offensive spell for the mid-tier ranger, similar to Hail of Thorns, but slightly better. It seems somewhat underpowered when you analyze it on its own, but it synergizes well with the class’s other features. It’s probably the best damage-dealing 3rd-level spell available to the ranger.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Lightning Arrow is a 3rd level Ranger spell from the Player’s Handbook. Your Ranger gets two 3rd level spell slots per long rest at 9th level. A that level, a Ranger can know a total of 6 spells, so you need to choose your spells carefully. Should you pick Lightning Arrow over other spells?</summary></entry></feed>